{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>Cardinal Innitzer offered aid for this event, only to be told that its home country had\u201cneither cardinals nor cannibals.\u201d</b><em><b> The New York Times</b></em><b>\u2019 Walter Duranty won a Pulitzer Prize for his correspondence work, which explicitly denied this event. In 2007, the (+) Verkhovna Rada declined to vote on a bill that would criminalize the denial of this event; that bill was proposed by Viktor (*) </b> Yushchenko. The possession of food was a criminal offense during, for the point, what 1932-33 Soviet-engineered genocide in which over three million Ukrainians starved to death?", "answer": "<b> Holodomor</b> (prompt on descriptions of a<b> Soviet famine</b> in<b> Ukraine</b>; do not accept or prompt \u201cHolocaust\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Richard Brewer was appointed the leader of a group with this name by John B. Wilson. That group was created to catch the killers of John Tunstall. William Tyrod defeated a force with this name, led by Herman Husband, at the Battle of Alamance in North Carolina.</b> <b>One group of this name employed Billy the Kid during the (+)</b> <b>Lincoln County War.</b> <b>A militia group of this name was led by Charles Jackson in Shelby County, close to the Louisiana-Texas border, in a cattle-thieving conflict in which 40 people died in the (*)</b> 1840s. For the point, give this shared name of several 19th century forces, one of which fought a war with the Moderators, who used vigilante action to control the government.", "answer": "<b> Regulator</b>s (accept Lincoln Country<b> Regulator</b>s; do not accept vigilantes)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Both of these countries were thrown out of the 1987 World Juniors after the Punch-Up in Piestany. Paul Henderson scored the winning goal in a series between the national teams of these two countries in which Vladislav Tretiak backstopped the losing team. The (+) Luzhniki Palace of Sports was the site of the final four of eight games in the 1972 Summit Series between these two countries that was nicknamed the \u201cCold War on Ice\u201d and had been set up to facilitate better relations via (*)</b> hockey diplomacy. For the point, name these two Cold War hockey superpowers.", "answer": "<b> Canada and the Soviet Union</b> (accept the<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b> or <b>USSR</b> or<b> Sovetskij Soyuz</b>,<b> Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik</b>, or<b> SSSR</b> for Soviet Union; do not accept or prompt answers involving Russia)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This man lost power for five days in the midst of a crisis in which the Italian tanker Rose Mary was captured by the British. This leader\u2019s actions kicked off the Abadan Crisis. He was the victim of the 28 Mordad coup, which received assistance from Kermit (+) Roosevelt Jr. and General Norman Schwarzkopf Sr., who had trained the secret police force of his successor. Operation Ajax targeted this man\u2019s government after he sought to nationalize an industry controlled by the (*)</b> Anglo-Persian Oil Company. For the point, name this Prime Minister of Iran who was ousted in an U.S. backed coup in 1953.", "answer": "Mohammad<b> Mosaddegh</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In a comic expressing panic over the potential success of this goal, Thomas Nast created the Republican elephant symbol. In attempting to accomplish this goal, Roscoe Conkling gave a speech with the line \u201che hails from Appomattox and its famous apple tree.\u201d The</b> <b>precedent that seemingly (+)</b> <b>prevented this action was downplayed due to its subject\u2019s</b> <b>youth. More delegates were pledged toward this goal than any other at the start of the 1880 convention, but it was (*)</b> unsuccessful. For the point, name this action which did not occur in either 1876 or 1880, as a former Union general followed George Washington\u2019s precedent and retired to private life instead.", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b> having a<b> third term</b> as President (or Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b> being<b> nominated </b>and/or<b> running for President for a third time</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This weapon used a programmable logic controller rootkit, but was designed to ignore victims that did not have the Step7 engineering platform, produced by Siemens. It used a</b> <b>series of four \u201czero day\u201d vulnerabilities to provide false feedback on (+)</b> <b>centrifuges that</b> <b>were instructed to spin themselves to failure. It is believed that this weapon was delivered in 2007 via a (*) </b> USB flash drive at a uranium enrichment plant. For the point, name this computer worm that, in 2007, attacked Iran\u2019s nuclear program.", "answer": "<b> Stuxnet</b> (prompt on descriptions of the computer worm that attacked Iran\u2019s nuclear plant before appropriate clues have been given)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>One possibly apocryphal story claims that Socrates saved the life of this man at the battle of Potidaea. This exile, who was allegedly killed in Phrygia by agents of Pharnabazus,</b> <b>held his last command at the battle of Notium. Critias helped orchestrate the (+)</b> <b>return</b> <b>of this man to his home city, years after he was accused of desecrating the Hermai statues. With (*)</b> Nicias and Lamachus, this man led the Sicilian Expedition. For the point, name this Athenian general of the Peloponnesian War who later defected to Sparta.", "answer": "<b> Alcibiades</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This location is the current home of</b><em><b> The Tent of Darius</b></em><b>, a work by the decorator and painter Charles le Brun.</b><em><b> Austerlitz</b></em><b> by Fran\u00b8cois G\u00b4erard and</b><em><b> Bouvines</b></em><b> by Horace Vernet</b> <b>are among the largest paintings in this location\u2019s (+)</b> <b>\u201cBattles Gallery.\u201d An antechamber</b> <b>in this location contains a Charpentier painting of a famous resident who maintained an 86-acre (*)</b> \u201cPetit Domaine\u201d here, Marie Antoinette. For the point, name this opulent royal palace of Louis XIV [fourteenth], known for its Hall of Mirrors.", "answer": "Chateau de<b> Versailles</b> [vayr-SYE] (or Palace of<b> Versailles</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader effectively broke off relations with the United States by repeatedly shouting\u201cTo hell with your aid!\u201d An early teacher of this man was Omar Said Tjokroaminoto. This man contrasted \u201cNekolim,\u201d or neocolonialism, with \u201cNefo,\u201d or \u201cNew Emerging Forces.\u201d He formulated the Pantjasila, or Five (+) Principles, for his new state. This man was targeted by a failed army coup called the September 30th Movement, and established (*)</b> \u201cGuided Democracy\u201d. For the point, what first president of independent Indonesia was succeeded by Suharto?", "answer": "<b> Sukarno</b> (or<b> Soekarno</b>; accept<b> Kusnasosro</b>; prompt on Bung Karno)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>One ruler with this name tried to institute hereditary succession with the Erbreichsplan [erb-rikes-plan]. After marrying Queen Constance, a ruler with this name became King of</b> <b>Sicily. Prior to marrying Geoffrey of Anjou, Empress (+)</b> <b>Matilda was married to a ruler</b> <b>of this name. A ruler with this name signed the Concordat of Worms with Pope Callixtus II. After being (*)</b> excommunicated, one ruler with this name stood outside of Canossa for three days in the snow in order to repent. For the point, give this name of seven Holy Roman Emperors, the fourth of whom feuded with Pope Gregory VII during the Investiture Controversy.", "answer": "<b> Henry</b> (or<b> Heinrich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Paul Foot has written on the coincidence of the central role of a rigged Toshiba cassette radio in both this event and activities in Frankfurt. This event was originally blamed on</b> <b>Palestinian nationalist groups and the \u201cUlster (+)</b> <b>Defence League,\u201d before the discovery</b> <b>of a suitcase apparently connected to Abdelbaset al-Megrahi. The only person convicted for this event was a Libyan intelligence officer who may have acted on the orders of (*) </b>Muammar Gaddafi. For the point, name this December 1988 terrorist attack in which Pan Am Flight 103 was bombed over a Scottish town.", "answer": "<b> Lockerbie bombing</b> (or<b> bombing of Pan Am Flight 103</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was fined under the Gayssot Act for calling the Holocaust \u201cjust a detail in the history of World War II,\u201d and he once used a pun about a \u201ccrematorium\u201d to refer to his rival, Michel Durafour. This man was routed in a 2002 election by a man using the slogan</b> <b>\u201cVote for the (+)</b> <b>Crook, not the Fascist.\u201d He was succeeded as party leader by his own</b> <b>daughter, who finished third in 2012 presidential voting behind (*)</b> Hollande and Sarkozy. For the point, name this father of Marine, a right-wing French politician who led the National Front party until 2011.", "answer": "Jean-Marie<b> Le Pen</b> Page 4", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>In a parody of this literary work, Ernest Crosby wrote about places with \u201cno cheerful iron mills\u201d or \u201cdepartment stores.\u201d This text tells people to be done with \u201cthe lightly proffered laurel.\u201d Both clergyman H.T. Johnson and journalist E.D. Morel wrote responses to this poem that changed one word in its title. Published with the subtitle \u201cThe (+) United States and the Philippine Islands,\u201d this poem begins with lines saying \u201csend forth the (*) </b> best ye breed\u201d and exhorts the listener to \u201ctake up\u201d the title entity. For the point, name this Rudyard Kipling poem frequently used to support imperialism.", "answer": "The<b> White Man\u2019s Burden</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b>On the night of this event, John Cole suggested that the crowd attracted to this event would \u201cnot be so public\u201d as he dined at Sabin\u2019s Tavern.</b><em><b> An Oration, Upon the Beauties of </b><b>Liberty</b></em><b> by preacher John Allen repeatedly referenced this event, which was led by Abraham</b> <b>Whipple. In this event, Captain (+)</b> <b>Lindsey\u2019s evasive maneuvers in the packet sloop</b> <em><b>Hannah</b></em><b> forced William Dudingston\u2019s ship (*)</b> onto a sandbar, after which the Sons of Liberty got vengeance for that ship\u2019s harassment of Narragansett Bay. For the point, name this June 1772 event in Rhode Island, in which a British ship was controversially burned.", "answer": "<b> Gaspee</b> Affair (accept descriptions of the burning, etc. of the<b> Gaspee</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The founder of this dynasty converted to Catholicism after signing the Union of Krewo and entered a personal union with his southern neighbour after he married Queen Jadwiga.</b> <b>When this dynasty\u2019s last ruler (+)</b> <b>Sigismund II, died childless, an elected monarchy was</b> <b>created through the Union of Lublin. Vytautas the Great\u2019s forces assisted this dynasty\u2019s founder in beating the (*) </b> Teutonic Knights at the Battle of Grunwald. For the point, name this dynasty that united Poland and Lithuania in the 14th through 16th centuries.", "answer": "<b> Jagiellon</b>ian Dynasty Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this American magazine that names an annual\u201cPerson of the Year.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Time</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s defense of Fabre d\u2019Eglantine led to a threat on his life. After Charles-Francois Dumouriez defected to the Austrians, this man was accused of treason. Before his execution, this man said \u201cDon\u2019t forget to (+) show my head to the people. It\u2019s well worth seeing.\u201d For opposing the Reign of Terror, this man was executed, but not before accurately predicting the death of his former (*) </b> ally, who was executed in the Thermidorian Reaction. For the point, name this first president of the Committee of Public Safety and former ally of Maximilien Robespierre.", "answer": "Georges<b> Danton</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Magnus Barefoot died during one of these events. In Ireland, these events often resulted in the creation of a longphort. Odo, Count of Paris was made a king following his successes during one of these events. The first recorded event of this type occurred on Portland, which</b> <b>resulted in the death of a (+)</b> <b>reeve. One of these events resulted in the abandonment of</b> <b>Iona Abbey. In an early one of these events, St. (*)</b> Cuthbert\u2019s remains were moved when the Isle of Lindisfarne was attacked. For the point, name these attacks carried out by seafaring Norsemen.", "answer": "<b> Viking raid</b>s (or equivalents; prompt on raids or equivalents alone) Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A plan to obtain these objects was known as Operation Moolah. The Catalina Affair was sparked when these objects approached Swedish vehicles. A key component of these objects was directly copied from the Rolls-Royce Nene. These objects were analyzed after</b> <b>Viktor Belenko brought one codenamed \u201cFoxbat\u201d to (+)</b> <b>Hokkaido in 1972. During a run</b> <b>involving one of these objects, Yuri Gagarin was killed. These objects named an (*)</b> \u201calley\u201dalong the Yalu River, where they would frequently clash with the F-86 Sabre. For the point, name these Soviet fighter jets.", "answer": "<b> MiG</b> fighter jets (or<b> Mikoyan-Gurevich</b>; accept specific types such as the<b> MiG-15</b> or the <b>MiG-25</b>; prompt on (fighter) jets or equivalents) (29) <b>This early president of the American Bible Society claimed the \u201cChristian Religion\u201d</b> <b>was \u201cthe fundamental precept of governance.\u201d This man lost a gubernatorial election to</b> <b>George Clinton after three counties\u2019 votes were (+)</b> <b>disqualified. He claimed to have been</b> <b>able to travel from Boston to Philadelphia in the light of his burning effigies. This man was the principal American negotiator of a (*) </b> treaty eliminating British control of forts in the Northwest Territory. For the point, name this namesake of a 1795 treaty regulating trade between the U.S. and Great Britain, who was also the first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. ANSWER: John<b> Jay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one depiction, this man smokes a cigarette as he stands next to a box reading \u201cIn counting there is strength.\u201d In another depiction, this man cannot fit in the \u201cCity Jail\u201das a caption reads \u201cstone walls do not a prison make.\u201d This person is depicted an obese</b> <b>vulture in a drawing captioned \u201cLet Us (+)</b> <b>Prey\u201d and as a man with a money bag for a</b> <b>head in an engraving titled \u201cThe Brains.\u201d Officials in Vigo, Spain, arrested him because they recognized his (*)</b> depictions in<em> Harper\u2019s Weekly</em>. For the point, name this \u201cboss\u201d of Tammany Hall\u2019s political machine, frequently assailed by cartoonist Thomas Nast.", "answer": "William \u201cBoss\u201d<b> Tweed</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Shortly after the end of this conflict, an Arab League summit was held in Cairo; just hours after that, Gamal Abdel Nasser suffered a fatal heart attack. The winning side in this</b> <b>conflict received military training from General (+)</b> <b>Zia ul-Haq. This conflict was sparked</b> <b>by the establishment of a \u201cRevolutionary airport\u201d at Dawson\u2019s Field, leading King Hussein to declare martial law. A group (*) </b> named after this conflict took hostage and killed 11 Israeli athletes during the 1972 Munich Olympics. For the point, name this month long civil war in Jordan that led to the expulsion of the PLO.", "answer": "<b> Black September</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>An early scene in this opera features the song \u201cMir ist so wunderbar,\u201d called the Canon Quartet. This was the first opera staged in Berlin after World War II, and the premiere of its first version was hampered by the presence of Napoleon\u2019s troops in Vienna. Rocco sings the (+) Gravedigging Duet with this opera\u2019s protagonist, who disguises herself as the title character to free her husband (*) </b> Florestan from political prison. Leonore is the hero of, for the point, what only opera composed by Ludwig van Beethoven?", "answer": "<b> Fidelio</b> Page 8", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b>In the prelude to this event, Roger Bushell said \u201cEveryone here in this room is living on borrowed time. By rights, we should all be dead!\u201d Dick Churchill was spared in the aftermath of this event due to his last name. Leonard Trent surrendered immediately after</b> <b>this event, after which he only received (+)</b> <b>solitary confinement. This event made use of</b> <b>three tunnels, codenamed Harry, Tom, and Dick, in case one of them was discovered by the (*)</b> Gestapo. For the point, name this event in which Allied soldiers fled from Stalag Luft III, a German POW camp, immortalized in a 1963 Steve McQueen film.", "answer": "The<b> Great Escape</b> (accept<b> escaping</b> from<b> Stalag Luft III</b> before the name is said; prompt on descriptions of \u201cescaping from a Nazi POW camp\u201d or similar before \u201cGerman\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In an off-the-cuff remark to a reporter, this man unwisely but correctly declared that\u201cOur next war will be with Germany.\u201d This man\u2019s attempt to run for the presidency on the Democratic ticket in 1900 was scuttled when he remarked that he would \u201cexecute the orders of Congress as (+) faithfully as I have executed the laws of my superiors.\u201d This man annihilated the fleet of Patricio Montojo y Pasaron by issuing the order \u201cYou (*) </b> may fire when you are ready, Gridley\u201d while on board his flagship, the USS<em> Olympia</em>. For the point, name this admiral who commanded the fleet that won the Battle of Manila Bay.", "answer": "George<b> Dewey</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Taylor Report recommended safety changes at these places in the aftermath of a fatal incident in one of them. Archibald Leitch designed dozens of these locations, including one at Ibrox that suffered hundreds of casualties twice: due to a structural collapse in 1902,</b> <b>and a (+)</b> <b>human pile-up in 1971. In retaliation for the assassinations of the Cairo Gang</b> <b>earlier in the day, Black and Tans opened fire into a crowd at one of these locations. A disastrous human (*)</b> crush led to the deaths of 96 people at one of these locations called Hillsborough. For the point, name these places, such as London\u2019s Wembley, which host certain sporting events.", "answer": "<b> soccer stadium</b>s (prompt on football stadiums) Page 9", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This dynasty suffered the tyranny of Dong Zhuo, who was opposed by the Guangdong Coalition. Sima Qian served as a court astrologer during this dynasty, whose history he</b> <b>recorded to finish his massive (+)</b> <em><b>Records of the Grand Historian</b></em><b>. This dynasty survived</b> <b>a peasant uprising that is depicted in (*)</b><em> Romance of the Three Kingdoms</em>; that uprising was led by Zhang Jue and his brothers and was named for the yellow turbans worn by the rebels. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that ruled in 1 AD and names the majority ethnic group of China.", "answer": "<b> Han</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>John Campbell plotted a sneak attack on this city that Bernardo de Galvez discovered. This city was the capital of the territory where the Chickasaw wars occurred, and the (+) pirate Jean Lafitte</b> <b>[la-feet] aided in its defense against Edward Pakenham. Adrien de Pauger mapped this city, then argued for its superiority to nearby (*)</b> Biloxi. For the point, name this city defended by Andrew Jackson in January 1815 after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent.", "answer": "<b> New Orleans</b> (or<b> Nouvelle-Orl\u00b4eans</b>) Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}